Patrick Emami

516 Weil Hall Phone: +1 (904) 962 8293 1949 Stadium Rd Email: pemami@ufl.edu

Gainesville, FL 32603 Home: https://pemami4911.github.io

Research Statement

I am a machine learning researcher working on scene representation learning, reinforcement learning, and AI for social good. My research has spanned topics including object-centric deep generative modeling, low-resource multi-object tracking, and traffic signal control. Mostly, I am curious about developing agents capable of learning challenging behaviors by reasoning about the world at the level of objects, like humans do.

Education

| $2016-2021^{\dagger}$ | University of Florida, Gainesville, FL | Advisor: Dr. Sanjay Ranka |
|-----------------------|--|---------------------------|
| | Ph.D., Computer Science (Machine Learning) | |
| | Thesis: Neural algorithms for object-centric scene understanding | |
| Summer 2019 | University College London, London, UK | Marc Deisenroth & |
| | Machine Learning Summer School (MLSS) | Arthur Gretton |
| 2012–2016 | University of Florida, Gainesville, FL | |
| | B.Sc., Computer Engineering | Cum Laude, GPA: 3.74/4.0 |

Research Experience

National Renewable Energy Lab (NREL), Research intern. May 2021–August 2021

• Regional Mobility.

Developed deep reinforcement learning algorithms for NEMA-compliant traffic control using a "digital twin" of the Chattanooga, Tennessee road network.

MALT Lab, Graduate Research Assistant. 2016-present

• EfficientMORL. ICML'21 [Github].

We re-interpret iterative assignment of pixels to object-centric slots as bottom-up inference in a hierarchical variational autoencoder. EfficientMORL has three key components: bottom-up inference with transformer-like attention to estimate an initial posterior over slots, a top-down prior to regularize and disentangle the slots, and lightweight iterative refinement to stabilize training. It is the first object-centric generative model to learn symmetric and disentangled representations while being computationally efficient.

• Stochastic object-centric world models. NeurIPS '20 ORLR Workshop Spotlight. [Github]

Proposed a latent state space model based on variational autoencoders for jointly learning object-centric representations and dynamics for stochastic real-world video. Formulated the integration of a stochastic latent dynamics model with segmentation-based object discovery and a novel sampling-based variational objective to fit environment stochasticity. Demonstrated superior object decomposition and stochastic future prediction on a robotic manipulation benchmark compared to prior work.

UF Transportation Institute (UFTI), Graduate Research Assistant. 2017–present.

• Sensible. NSF Grant 1446813, 2017–present. [Open source release forthcoming]

Software engineering lead for Sensible, a distributed Python framework for real-time multi-sensor multi-object tracking at traffic intersections. Supports V2X communication and intersections with multiple roads each equipped with multiple sensors such as Econolite cameras and Smartmicro radars. Achieves GPU-less video tracking with a novel deep convolutional network running on PyTorch. Integrates with a real-time traffic signal optimizer for advanced adaptive signal control.

Publications

Peer-Reviewed Journals

- [1] He, P., & **Emami, P.**, & Ranka, S., & Rangarajan, A. Learning Scene Dynamics From Point Cloud Sequences. IJCV. 2021. *Under review*.
- [2] **Emami, P.**, & Elefteriadou, L., & Ranka, S. Long-range Multi-Object Tracking at Traffic Intersections on Low-Power Devices. IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems. 2021. [UFTI article]
- [3] **Emami, P.**, & Pardalos, P. M., & Elefteriadou, L., & Ranka, S. Machine Learning Methods for Data Association in Multi-Object Tracking. ACM Computing Surveys, 53, 4, Article 69. 2020.
- [4] Pourmehrab, M., Emami, P., Martin-Gasulla, M., Wilson, J., Elefteriadou, L., Ranka, S. Signalized Intersection Performance with Automated and Conventional Vehicles: A Comparative Study. Journal of Transportation Engineering, Part A: Systems 146.9. 2020.

Peer-Reviewed Conferences and Workshops

- [1] **Emami, P.**, He, P., Ranka, S, Rangarajan, A. Efficient Iterative Amortized Inference for Learning Symmetric and Disentangled Multi-Object Representations. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML'21). 2021. **21.5% acceptance rate**.
- [2] **Emami, P.**, He, P., Rangarajan, A., Ranka, S. A Symmetric and Object-Centric World Model for Stochastic Environments. 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems Workshop on Object Representations for Learning and Reasoning (NeurIPS '20). 2020. **Spotlight**.
- [3] **Emami, P.***, Vargas, L.*, Traynor, P. On the Detection of Disinformation Campaign Activity with Network Analysis. CCSW 2020: The ACM Cloud Computing Security Workshop. 2020. *Equal contribution
- [4] **Emami, P.**, Pourmehrab, M., Martin-Gasulla, M., Ranka, S., Elefteriadou, L. A Comparison of Intelligent Signalized Intersection Controllers Under Mixed Traffic. IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference, 2018.
- [5] Omidvar, A., Pourmehrab, M., **Emami, P.**, Kiriazes, R., Esposito, J., Letter, C., Elefteriadou, L., Ranka, S., Crane, C. Deployment and Testing of Optimized Autonomous and Connected Vehicle Trajectories at a Closed-Course Signalized Intersection. Transportation Research Board's 97th, 2018.
- [6] **Emami, P.**, & Pourmehrab, M., & Elefteriadou, L., & Ranka, S., & Crane, C. A Demonstration of Fusing DSRC and Radar for Optimizing Intersection Performance. Automated Vehicles Symposium (AVS'17), 2017.
- [7] **Emami, P.**, Elefteriadou, L., Ranka, S. Tracking Vehicles Equipped with Dedicated Short-Range Communication at Traffic Intersections. 7th ACM International Symposium on Design and Analysis of Intelligent Vehicular Networks and Applications (DIVANet'17), 2017.
- [8] Hamlet, A., **Emami, P.**, Crane, C. The Cognitive Driving Framework: Joint Inference for Collision Prediction and Avoidance in Autonomous Vehicles. In the 15th International Conference on Control, Automation and Systems (ICCAS), pp. 1714-1719. IEEE, 2015.
- [9] Hamlet, A., Emami, P., Crane, C. A Gesture Recognition System for Mobile Robots That Learns Online. In the 2014 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS'14), pp. 2114-2119. IEEE, 2014.

Preprints

[1] **Emami, P.**, & Ranka, S. Learning Permutations with Sinkhorn Policy Gradient. arXiv:1805.07010 [cs.LG], 2018.

[2] **Emami, P.**, & Panos M. P., & Elefteriadou, L., & Ranka, S. Machine Learning Methods for Solving Assignment Problems in Multi-Target Tracking. Under review at ACM Computing Surveys. arXiv:1802.06897 [cs.CV], 2018.

Blog Posts

[1] **Emami, P.** Deep Deterministic Policy Gradients in Tensorflow. http://pemami4911.github.io/blog/2016/08/21/ddpg-rl.html. 2016. > 100K unique views (Google Analytics). [Github]

Professional Activities

| 2022 | International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), Reviewer |
|-----------|---|
| 2021 | Computer Vision and Image Understanding (CVIU), Reviewer |
| 2021 | International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), Reviewer |
| 2021 | Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), Reviewer |
| 2021 | International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), Reviewer |
| 2021 | IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference (ITSC), Reviewer |
| 2021 | Transportation Research Record (TRR), Reviewer |
| 2020 | NeurIPS Workshop on Interp. Inductive Biases and Phys., Reviewer |
| 2020 | Transportation Research Board Annual Meeting (TRBAM), Reviewer |
| 2020 | Optimization Letters, Reviewer |
| 2019 | UF Informatics Institute Student Data Analysis Seminar, Co-Organizer |
| 2018 | UF Informatics Institute Student Data Analysis Seminar, Co-Organizer |
| 2018 | International Conference on Machine Learning and Data Science , Reviewer |
| 2018 | IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference , Special Session Chair |
| 2018 | IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference (ITSC), Reviewer |
| 2017 | International Conference on Machine Learning and Data Science , Reviewer |
| 2017 | UF Informatics Institute Student Data Analysis Seminar, Co-Organizer |
| 2016–2018 | UF Machine Learning Reading Group, Organizer |

Professional Societies

| Alpha Epsilon Lambda Graduate Honor Society, member |
|---|
| ACM, student member |
| IEEE, student member |
| IEEE Eta Kappa Knu Honor Society, member |
| |

Selected Honors and Awards

Top 10% Reviewer at ICML'21

2020 Student of the Year USDOT STRIDE Center (10 universities) (\$1,000)

2016–present McKnight Doctoral Fellowship (\$65,000)

2016–present CISE Department Graduate Research Fellowship (\$150,000)

2016 President's Honor Roll

2015–2016 Northrop Grumman Engineering Scholarship (\$1,000) 2014–2015 University Scholars Program Research Grant (\$1,750)

2014 IROS'14 Best Entertainment Robots and Systems Paper Finalist

Mentoring

| Fall 2019–present | Yury Lebedev (Ph.D.) | Univ. of Florida |
|-------------------|--|------------------|
| Fall 2018–present | Kevin Chow (B.Sc., now Ph.D. at Tsinghua Univ.) | Univ. of Florida |
| Fall-Summer 2018 | Anuran Rouchowdhury (M.Sc) | Univ. of Florida |
| Summer 2018 | Ian Pelakh (B.Sc.) | Univ. of Florida |
| Fall 2017 | Shalaka Naik (M.Sc), Individual Study | Univ. of Florida |
| Fall 2017 | Vivek Gade (M.Sc), Individual Study | Univ. of Florida |
| Summer 2017 | Jabari Wilson (SURF Fellow, now Ph.D. at Univ. of Florida) | Univ. of Alabama |

Teaching & Volunteering

| Summer 2018 | Student Science Training Program, Instructor | |
|-------------|--|--|
| | Designed & taught a 6-week short course on machine learning basics | |
| 2017–2018 | Teaching Youth Programming Essentials, Curriculum Lead | |
| | Responsible for designing and improving the UF TYPE programming curriculum | |
| 2016–2017 | Teaching Youth Programming Essentials, Instructor | |
| | Teach an after school Intro to Programming course at local high schools | |
| 2014–2015 | Association of Computer Engineers, Co-Founder and Project Manager | |
| | Organized and presented at technical and professional development | |
| | workshops for undergraduate computer engineering students | |